<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony of the true Light of the world· Which is given to every man that comes into the world, and of the true measure of the gift of God, given to every one to profit withal. And a true witness, and faithful: ... / Given forth for the good of all people, in pity to all souls, by him who is not known to the world, but a stranger in it, Geo. Fox.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84817</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1929</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E902_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204824</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864287</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864287</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116512</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84817)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116512)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 135:E902[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony of the true Light of the world· Which is given to every man that comes into the world, and of the true measure of the gift of God, given to every one to profit withal. And a true witness, and faithful: ... / Given forth for the good of all people, in pity to all souls, by him who is not known to the world, but a stranger in it, Geo. Fox.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
                  <author>Burrough, Edward, 1634-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>50, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and sold in his shop at the black Spread-Eagle, at the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: E.B., i.e. Edward Burrough.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 24. 1656"; the 7 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116512:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY Of the <hi>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E LIGHT</hi> Of the WORLD.</p>
            <p>Which is given to every man that comes into the world, and of the true meaſure of the gift of God, given to every one to profit withal.</p>
            <p>And a True Witneſs, and Faithful: Witneſſed of Chriſt Jeſus unto this generation, that every one may believe in the Light of the World, and receive eternal Life; or that every one may be left without excuſe, by the Light, which is the condemnation of all that believe not in it, but hates it: Wherein all may learn the way of Life, or know the condemnation from Life, into the pit of Darkneſs.</p>
            <p>Given forth for the good of all people, in pity to all ſouls, by him who is not known to the world, but a ſtranger in it, <hi>Geo. F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that loves the Light, his deeds are wrought in God, but he that hates the Light his deeds are evil.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and ſold in his Shop at the black Spread-Eagle, at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:116512:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116512:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Earth, the Teſtimony is true and everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which God hath given of the Son, and which the Son hath given of the Fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, and it abides for ever; the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtimony of Life in all that doth believe, and the Teſtimony of Death to all that believe not, even the light of the world, which lighteth every man that comes into the world; the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance unto eternal life, or the condemnation into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: and who ever turn from the light of the Son of God within them, and walks not in it, goes into the Error, and into the way of Perdition; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> who walks in the light, ſtumbles not, becauſe he ſees the light of this world, Chriſt Jeſus, the Author and the Finiſher of the Faith, and there is no other Saviour then he which was, is, and is to come, the light of the world; and who-ever preaches a Chriſt to beli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve in for ſalvation, who hath not lighted every man with the true light, preaches a falſe Chriſt, and not that Chriſt which the Prophets and <hi>John</hi> bore witneſs of, and which the Apoſtles witneſſed: So that this is truth from the Lord God, there is no o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her name given for ſalvation, but the name of Jeſus: nor there is no other Chriſt Jeſus, but he which lighteth every man that comes into the world with the true light; and except this Chriſt Ieſus be revealed by the ſpirit of the Father within, ſalvation is not received by him: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, all friends who have received the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtimony of the light of the Son of God within you, and have believed the report of the Father, and of the Son, hold f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt the word
<pb facs="tcp:116512:3"/> of that Teſtimony, and dwell in it, and walk in it up to the Father of light and life: and this is the power of God, in which you will be kept unto the day of ſalvation; and this is the power of God which will keep you from all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, and ſo from condemnation: and if any turn from the light, they run into the evil, and backſlides from the Truth: and ſuch ſhall bear their own ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, in the ſight of God, and all his children: For this is the meſſage which was, and is, that God is light, and in him is no darkneſs at all. All that dwels in the light, their habitation is in God, and they know a hiding place in the day of ſtorm; and they that dwell in the light, are built upon the rock, and cannot be moved, for who are moved or ſhaken, goes from the light, and ſo goes from their ſtrength, and from the power of God, and loſes the peace and the enjoyment of the preſence of God; for the light is the eye by which Gods preſence is ſeen and felt: and all that ever com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to the knowledge of God, muſt own the light which Chriſt hath lighted them withal, for there is no other way to the Father of life: And this is the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony which in the power of the Lord hath been born and given through Nations by his ſervants, and the day of your viſitation is upon you Nations, and Peoples: and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto the Father hath wrought, and the Son hath wrought, and the voice of Wiſdom hath been heard, but the night cometh when no man can work, and all that have not received the witn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs which God hath given con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Son, and all that goes from the teſtimony of the light within, and continues not therein unto the end, they ſhall be given up to fulfil the meaſure of Iniquity, and to run their race in the way to perdition, till they be ſealed in the pit of darkneſs and condemnation, where there is no repentance: and the Lord God Almighty is clear from all their blood, and their blood be upon their own head for ever, becauſe they hate the light, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves
<pb facs="tcp:116512:3"/> not in it, nor continues not unto the end, to walk therein. And this is the teſtimony which is given to me, to teſtifie, who is not of this wrrld, but a ſervant to him, whoſe Teſtimony never changeth, which is light.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>1ſt of the 11. mon. 1656.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>E. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116512:4"/>
            <head>Concerning the Light.</head>
            <p>HEre you may perceive that be in the light, a diſtinguiſh between them that walk in the light, the converted, and them that ſhines in darkneſs, that be unconverted; which are the ſtate of darkneſs, and the ſtate of the Apoſtles preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the world, and the Jews in the unconverted eſtate, and the eſtate of the Apoſtles writing to them that were converted, the Believers; and the ſtate of them that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Truth, who was out of the light, as you ſee the Jews which profeſſed the Scriptures of Truth, declared forth from the Spirit of Truth, and themſelves out of it out of the Spirit; they knew not Chriſt the light, the end of all the holy men of God ſpeakings and writings, and the end of all the types, and ſhadows, and figures; Him whom all the holy men of God gave teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mony of, and the Prophets of the Lord God. To all you that now be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſtians, and believeth not in the light that enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth every man that cometh, and yet profeſs Scripture, you are in the ſame nature the Iews were in, for they profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Scripture, but did not believe in the light which did enlighten every o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that cometh into the world, Chriſt Jeſus: So you and the Jews being one in profeſſing the Scriptures in words, but not believing in the light, you be both out of Covenant, ſo you cannot convert the Jews, for the conver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of them, is to bring them into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God, who brings them into Covenant with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116512:4"/> God, muſt be in the light, and believe in the light, which enlightneth every man that cometh into the world, that all men through him might believe: for ſaith God, Ile give him for a Covenant of light: God ſpeaks by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet before Chriſt is come, to put an end to the types and ſhaddows; Ile give him for a Covenant of light to the Gentiles, to enlighten them, and Ile make a new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the houſe of Iſrael, and the houſe of Judah: Mark, a new covenant with the Houſe of Iſrael and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, was Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt the light: So they that hold up the firſt covenant, and come not to the new, they was unconver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for thoſe was out of the light; ſo out of the light, out of converſion: and Ile give him for a covenant of light to the Gentiles, to enlighten them, ſo the Gentiles being in the light in the covenant, the Jews in the light in the covenant, they are both one with the Father; and this throws down the partition wall betwixt Jew and Gentile, and brings them to be both one in the covenant, in the light, and both one out of the covenant, out of the light, and to meaſure the Jew and the Gentile out of the light, out of the covenant, the Gentile ſhall judge the Jew, and make his circumciſion uncircumciſion, for the Jews having the Law of God, and was commanded to do ſuch things according to the Law, and did not do them, the Gentiles doing by nature the things contained in the Law, ſhewing the Law of God written in their hearts, without an outward command, ſo it was by Nature, for that which may be known of God, was man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>feſt in them, for God ſhewed it unto them, which when they acted contrary to it, they knew the judgements of the Lord did come upon them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo the Jews here having the Law in the letter, and was tranſgreſſors of the law of the outward, he who acts contrary to that of God within him, and the Gentiles who acted according to that of God in him, fulfilled the Law, this judged the Jew: ſo the one was a command as in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116512:5"/> time, and the other was not as a command, but he did it by nature, ſo according to the Apoſtles natural ſon.</p>
            <p>So you that ſtumble, and ſay Chriſt Jeſus doth not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten every one that cometh into the world, that all men might believe; Mark, God ſaid, he would give him for a light, for a covenant to enlighten the Gentiles, and thoſe was called Heathen: and God ſaid, Ile make a new co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with the Houſe of Iſrael. Theſe were called the people of God, and Chriſt was this covenant of light to the Jews, and to the Gentiles; and the Jews not believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in this covenant, nor the Gentiles, they were both in the unconverſion, and <hi>John</hi> a man ſent from God to bear witneſs to the true light, he ſaid, he was not the light, but ſaid, This was the true light that did enlighten every one that cometh into the world, and in Chriſt was life, and the life was the light of men. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, the light of men, and the light ſhined in darkneſs, and the darkneſs compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended it not: This was he that was in the world, and the world knew him not, though all things was made by him; and this was he that <hi>John</hi> came a witneſs of, that all men through him might believe; and this the true light that doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, which light ſhineth in darkneſs, and da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kneſs comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it not. Now mark, it is there. What? Doth it ſhine in darkneſs, and darkneſs comprehendeth it not? Is not this the ſtate that the world knew h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m not, nor the Phariſees knew him not, though the Kingdom of heaven was with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n them, <hi>Luk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 17. and light ſhined in darkneſs, and darkneſs comprehended it not. Her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'s the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted eſtate; ſo he came to his own, and his own receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him not; light ſhines in darkneſs, and darkneſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends it not: You were d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rkneſs ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. but now are ye light in the Lord. Walk as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the light. Now mark, Heres ſometimes: here is times of darkneſs, but now they were light in the Lord.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116512:5"/> Now here was the converted and the unconverted, and theſe were to have no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works of darkneſs; t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e light ſhines in darkneſs, though darkneſs doth not comprehend it, and ye are ſomtimes darkneſs, and light ſhines in d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rkneſs, and darkneſs doth not comprehend it; there is the unconverted eſtate, and the converted eſta e: an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God hath commanded light to ſhine out of da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kneſs, and hath ſhined in our hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt. Now mark, heres light ſhines out of darkn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs, God had commanded it to ſhine out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: What? Was it not there then? Now it is come forth; before it was in darkneſs, light ſhined in darkneſs, and God hath commanded it to ſhine out of darkneſs, and ſomtimes ye were darkneſs, but are the light of the Lord, which light that ſhines in the heart, gives the light of the knowledge of the glory of God, heres the conver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed eſtate. Now while light ſhineth in darkneſs, and darkneſs doth not comprehend it, theres the unconverted eſtate; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>John</hi> 1. and the Apoſtle was ſent to turn peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the darkneſs to the light, from the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan to God. Now this was the eſtate of preaching to them while they were in darkneſs, whom the God of the world ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h blinded their eyes, left the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt ſhould ſhine in them. Mark, ſhine in them, therefore the god of the world hath blinded the eye of the mind, and to ſuch the Goſpel is hid; for the light darkneſs cannot comprehend, while the god of the world hath blinded your minds; therefore the Apoſtle was ſent to turn them from darkneſs to the light, light ſhineth in darkneſs, ſo the god of the world hath blinded them, leſt the light of the glorious Goſpel ſhould ſhine in them. Now wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re it ſhines in the heart, it gives the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the glory of God, where it comes fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th, now where it ſhines in darkneſs, and darkneſs comprehends it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116512:6"/> not, theres the god of the world that hath blinded the mind, and to ſuch the Goſpel is hid, which is the power of God, and the light of the glorious Goſpel is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, which is the Image of God, and it doth not ſhine in them, to give them the light of the knowledge of God. Now ſuch as are turned to the light, the eye comes to be opened, and from the darkneſs theſe comes, and from the power of Satan, the god of the world, that hath blinded their eye, that the light of the glorious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel ſhines in them, to give them the light of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the glory of God, and to ſuch the Goſpel is not hid: So by the manifeſtation of the Truth commending our ſelves to every mans conſcience in the ſight of God. Now heres the ſtate not turned from the darkneſs to the light, and their eye is not opened; then the god of the world hath blinded them. Such be in the unconverted eſtate, to ſuch the Goſpel is hid, though light ſhines in darkneſs, and the god of the world blinds their minds: ſo this is the time they are darkneſs not turned from the da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kneſs, and the darkneſs doth not comprehend the light. Now where God hath commanded the light to ſhine out of darkneſs; Mark, out of darkneſs, ſuch are come to be turned from the darkneſs to the light, ſuch witneſſeth converſion, and the Image of God ſhines in them. But the other, the darkneſs cannot comprehend it, <hi>Acts</hi> 26. that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer and riſe again, and ſhew light to the people, and to the Gentiles, and this was the Apoſtles confeſſion before the heathen, when that they thought he had been mad, when he confeſſed the light the Heatheniſh Rulers did; and ſaid, that he was ſent to turn people from the darkneſs to the light; Now light ſhines in darkneſs, ſaith <hi>Iohn:</hi> and you were ſomtimes darkneſs ſaith the Apoſtle to the converted, and theſe that were to be turned from the darkneſs to the light, was the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. But where God hath commanded the light to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116512:6"/> ſhine out of darkneſs, to give the light of the knowledge of God, theſe be the converted: heres light comes out of darkneſs. So all you that doth not ſee the light which doth enlighten every one that cometh into the world, which ſhines in darkneſs, and darkneſs doth not c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it, and where light ſhines out of the darkneſs, it gives the light of the knowledge of the glory of God: you that do not ſee this, are the darkneſs yet, which do not comprehend the light; and the god of the world hath blinded their minds, and their eyes are not yet opened, and from darkneſs you are not yet turned, and in the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted ſtate you yet be, that the god of the world hath yet blinded your minds, leſt the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt ſhould ſhine in you, which doth enlighten eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that cometh into the world; ſo what communion hath light with darkneſs, it is an unequal yoke, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. for light brings to have fellowſhip with God, communion with God, but darkneſs cannot comprehend it: and thus the Apoſtle who was ſent to turn people from the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the light, warning both ſmall and great, which made the heatheniſh Rulers to think that he was mad: To turn people now from the darkneſs to the light, and to profeſs the light is the ſame as it was then, and them that are wondering, and thinks them beſides themſelves, that ſpeaks of the light to them, their eies are not yet opened; ſo your eyes muſt be opened before you ſee the light: ſo he that believes the light, ſhall not abide in darkneſs, but he ſhall have the light of life. Mark, the light ſhines in darkneſs there, but he that believes in the light, ſhall not abide there; but he ſhall have the light of l fe: ſo if any man walks in the night, he ſtumbles, becauſe there is no light in him, in him that walks in the night. Mark, he walks in darkneſs, and it is his time of darkneſs, and theſe are them that ſees not Chriſt the light, that doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, yet light ſhines in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116512:7"/> darkneſs, but he that walks in the light, theres no occaſion of ſtumbling in him; but he that walks in the night, he ſtumbles, becauſe there is no light in him, for he is from the light, for light ſhines in darkneſs, and darkneſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nds it not. Here you may ſee him who ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>des not in the truth, but walks in the night, endures not light, he that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lks in the night goes from the light, and hates the li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ht, becauſe his deeds are evil, and will not come to the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght, becauſe the light will reprove him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 11. ſo while you have the light, walk in the light, leſt darkneſs come upon you: for he that walks in the darkneſs, knows not whither he goes; and while you have the light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the light, that you may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>come children of the light, ſo b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lieving in the light, you become a child of the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght: I am come a light into the world, that whoſoever believeth in me, ſhould not abide in darkneſs. Mark, he is to come out of darkneſs, he is not to abide there, he that believes in Chriſt the light of the world. Now who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſaith he believeth in Chriſt, and abides in darkneſs his belief is falſe, <hi>John</hi> 12. but whoſoever believeth in the light, ſhould not abide in darkneſs, he comes to have death abol ſhed, and hath brought life and immortality to light through the Goſpel, thats the power of God, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. and who ſees this, knows him who hath immortality dwelling in the light, heres the converted eſtate: And Brethren, ye are not in darkneſs, that the day ſhould over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take you as a thief, but ye are all the chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dren of the light, and of the day; and not of the night, nor of darkneſs. Mark, the Apoſtle ſaith, they was not in da kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs, and ſo the day ſhould not come upon them as a thie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; and mark, how the day wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l come upon them who be in the darkneſs that comprehends not the light; that be in the time of light ſhining in darkneſs, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rkneſs doth not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it, upon ſuch the day will c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me as a thief. Mark, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he day will come as a thief. What a wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d is this upon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116512:7"/> them that are not the children of light, but upon them that be darkneſs, where light is not comprehended? 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. A light to the Gentil s, a glory to Iſrael. Mark, a light to them that are called heathen, and a glory to the people of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. And here one ſaw the fulfilling of the prophets, he that ſaw his ſalvation, ſaw the glory of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, and the light of the Gentiles: ſo doth every one that ſeeth their ſalvation, they ſee the light that ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eneth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that cometh into the world, the glory of Iſrael, and the glory of the Gentiles. Now ſaith Chriſt to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, what I tell you in the darkneſs, that ſpeak you in light; and what I tell you in the ear, that preach you on the houſe top, and be not afraid of him that kills the body. Mark what condition theſe was in when this was ſpoken to them, when he told them there was nothing covered that ſhould not be revealed, and hid that ſhall not be known, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. and ſaith Chriſt, the light of the body is the eye, if therefore thy eye be ſingle, thy whole body ſhall be full of light. Mark, if thy eye be ſingle, make ſearch, and ſee if it be ſo, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6 but if thy eye be evil, thy whole body is full of darkneſs: Mark, theres place for it, if therefore the light that be in thee be da k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, how great is that darkneſs? ſuch are ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ving Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and the contrary maſter, to ſuch heres the diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and laying up for themſelves treaſure upon earth, where the eye is not ſingle; and ſuch puts light for dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and darkneſs for light: So Chriſt was called with the Jews a Prince of Divels: So the light that was in you was darkneſs, yet Chriſt told them the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven was within them, and the Kingdom of Heaven is light; and John ſaith, Light ſhines in darkneſs, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs doth not comprehend it; and the Apoſtle ſaith, God hath commanded light to ſhine out of darkneſs; ſo the light comprehendeth darkneſs, and gives the light of the knowledge of God, and the people of God that ſate in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116512:8"/> darkneſs, ſaw a light, and to them that ſate in the ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death, light is ſprung up. Here was the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted eſtate, and the converted eſtate, when they ſate in darkneſs, and the ſhaddow of death, theres the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, but them that was converted, light was ſprung up, but darkneſs could not comprehend it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. but who is come to witneſs the day <hi>Zachary</hi> ſpeaks of, that the light would not be clear nor dark, but at the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſhall be light: This was the day when the living water was to go out from Jeruſalem, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14. who ſees that which <hi>Habakuk</hi> ſaw, <hi>Hab.</hi> 3. the glory of the Lord covered the earth, whoſe glory was his praiſe, whoſe brightneſs was as the light, and the judgements of the Lord God and his Son, are as the light that goeth forth; for who acts contrary to the light, God who is light, his judgements are according to the light, and are one with the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght, and anſwers the light in every one, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. he ſaw when he was broug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t out of the darkneſs into the light, ſo theres a time in darkneſs, and a time out of darkneſs, but he ſaw each condition, who come under that which was tranſgreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, ſuch as provokes the Lord to anger, to ſuch the Lord ſaid he would take away their light of the candle, ſuch as tranſgreſs the ways of the Lord, <hi>Ier.</hi> 25. but ſuch as hears the word of the Lord, they come to witneſs the ſtate, where they ſhall not need the light of the Sun, nor the light of the Moon, nor the light of a candle: but who tranſgreſs the word of the Lord, ſhall want the light of a candle; ſo to the Law and the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no light in them. Mark, how ſhould they when they have tranſgreſſed it, and loves darkneſs more then light, and are gone from it, ſo gone from the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony; which is the Spirit of Propheſie, which is the teſtimony of Jeſus, and ſpeaks not according to the word, which is light in them; ſo who are gone from the word,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116512:8"/> are gone from the light, and where the word is tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the light condems them, for the light comes from the word; Chriſt whoſe name is called the word of God, which enlightneth every man that cometh into the world; and the law is light, and heres the ſtate of darkneſs, where theres no light in them which comprehended not the light, which be in the tranſgreſſion, and theres the place for the familiar ſpirit to enter. Now if ye ſay the Letter be the Teſtimony, and the Letter be the Law, Iſa. 7. the Phariſees they had the Letter, which ſtood againſt Chriſt the ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and they had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Law, if that be the Law, and if that be the word, and they ſtood againſt Chriſt the light, which had the words of the Law: for mark, them that have tranſgreſſed the light, which is the Law, they are from the teſtimony, and they are from the light, and then theres no light in them, and ſuch was the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, which profeſſed the Scriptures, and doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the light when it was come, yet light ſhines in darkneſs, but darkneſs doth not comprehend it, and theres that which is dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, which before converſion muſt be quickned; ſo the people that have walked in darkneſs, have ſeen a great light, and they that have dwelt in a land of the ſhaddow of death, hath light ſhined. I ſay, and they who tranſgreſſed, who were from the Law and the Teſtimony, called darkneſs light, and and put light for darkneſs, this was the darkneſs which could not comprehend it in the Tranſgreſſion, now with the light theſe were comprehended. The Prophet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended theſe who was not in the light, and ſpake not according to the Word, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ſpake not according to Chriſt, which the Prophet ſaid that God would give him for a covenant of light to the Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iles, and to op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the blind eyes, and to bring out the priſoner from the priſon, and them that ſate in darkneſs from the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſon-houſe, Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, what is, the Priſoner muſt come out here, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116512:9"/> muſt come into covenant with God, doth not the light come to ſhine out of darkneſs here, where the Priſoner comes out, and is he not in darkneſs till that? I have long held my peace, and have been ſtill, I w ll bring the blind by a way they know not, and will lead them into paths that they have not known, I will make their darkneſs light; now you that a e bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd cannot comprehend the light, ſuch ſtands againſt the covenant of God, and ſees it not that be blind, but ſuch now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Lord God is come to lead, to make darkneſs light, and to lead them the way they have not known, Iſa. 42. Moreover, ſaith the Lord, the light of the Moon ſhall be as the light of the Sun, and the light of the Sun as the light of ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en days, Iſa. 30. and ſaith the Lord, is it a light thing that thou ſhouldeſt be as my ſervant, to ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe up the ſeed of J cob, and to reſtore the preſerved of Iſrael. Mark, to reſtore them, heres Covenant with God, I will give thee for a light to the Gentiles, that thou mayſt be my ſalvation to the ends of the earth: Mark, Now you that ſay h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doth not enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en every man that cometh into the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld, you ſee not the ſalvation of the ends of the earth; Iſa. 49. who is among you that feareth the Lord, and obeyeth the voice of his ſervant, that walks in darkneſs, and hath no light. Mark, that walks in darkneſs, hath no light, while he walks in darkneſs, what l ght hath he there, let him truſt in the name of the Lord, and ſtay upon his God; then he ſtays upon the light, but if he walks in darkneſs, he goes from the light; and whoſo feareth the Lord, and obeyeth the voice of his ſervant, that will lead him out of darkneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght, Iſa. 50. and ſuch comes to find the help of God: But ſuch as walks in darkneſs, goes from the light and fear of God, and ſtays not upon the Lord, and ſuch comes to have no light, for darkneſs cannot comprehend it, though light ſhines in darkneſs, yet darkneſs cannot comprehend it, ſo they will put light for darkneſs, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116512:9"/> darkneſs for light, which is comprehended with the light, which reacheth to the light which ſhines in darkneſs: Darkneſs ſhall cover the earth, and groſs darkneſs the people: Mark, cover: and light ſhines in darkneſs, but the Lord ſhall riſe upon thee, and his glory ſhall be ſeen in thee, and the Gen iles ſhall come to thy light: Ariſe, ſhine, for the light is come, and the glory of the Lord is riſen; then ſhall thy l ght break forth as the morning, and thy light ſpeedily; and thy righteouſneſs ſhall go before thee, and the Sun ſhall be no more thy light by day, nor the Moon give light to thee, but the Lord God ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll be thy everlaſting light: heres converſion, thy light riſeth in obſcurity, and thy darkneſs ſhall be as the Noon-day: read that condition, heres converſion again, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. and 60. ſuch as came out of bondage, out of captivity, out of tranſgreſſion, the Lord had enlightned them, and given them a nail in h s holy Place. Mark, a nail, a faſtning. Mark, and read what a nail doth, but ſuch as be in the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptivity, tranſgreſſion, and bondage, darkneſs, covering, therefore light ſhineth, and darkneſs comprehendeth it not, thou wilt ſave the afflicted, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing down the proud. Look, thou wilt lighten my candle, oh Lord! and enlighten my darkneſs. Mark, as the afflicted is ſaved, proud looks is brought down, the candle is lighted, and theres enlightning of darkneſs. Mark, the enlightning of darkneſs, that l ght ſees over it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. and they look'd to the Lord, and unto him, and were enlightned. Mark, as theres a looking to the Lord, theres an enlightning, yea which makes the face to ſhine, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. but looking from the Lord, and going from the light, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ates it, he goes into darkneſs, and there he ſtumbles, if it be at Noon-day, they were ſtumbling when Chriſt was among them, the Phariſees, the Scribes, the Jews, which had Scriptures, but were darkneſs, and in darkneſs, and the light ſhined in them, but they could not comprehend it, and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116512:10"/> of heaven was within them, but they were obſerving it to come, Lo here, and lo there: and of <hi>David</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh Chriſt came, ſaid his lightning enlightned the world, and the earth ſaw and trembled. Mark, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned the world; you will ſay he enlightens Saints, but his light enlightens the world, and the earth ſaw and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 97. He ſpread the cloud for a covering, and fire to give light in the night. Mark, who be in the night, there was fire to give th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m light in the night to ſtay upon, whereby they m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght ſtay upon the Lord, which was to the children of Iſrael, which had the figures of the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſubſtance Chriſt Je us, the enterance of thy words giveth light. Ma k, the entrance of the words of God giveth light, it is a true word, but you ſee the Phariſees had the words, and the mind that tranſgreſſed; ſo they hated the light Chriſt, they that had received the words from others: but the enterance of the words received from God, giveth light; if I ſay ſurely the darkneſs ſhall cover me, even the night ſhall be light about me, yea the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hideth not from thee, take notice of this, but the night ſhineth as the day, the darkneſs and the light are both alike to thee, for the Lord ſees over it, who is one with the light that ſhines in darkneſs, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. ye are the light of the world, ſaith Chriſt, who ſaith he was the light of the world, ſaid his Diſciples was the light of the world, Mark, the light of it, a City ſet on a hill that cannot be hid, neither do men light a candle and put it under a buſhel, but on a candleſtick, and is giveth light to all that be in the houſe; let the light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your father which is in heaven: here they anſwer the light which every man is enlightned withal, that are the light of the wo ld, which makes them to glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifie their father which is in heaven: and think not ſaith Chriſt, that I come to deſtroy the Law, but to fulfil it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116512:10"/> paths of the juſt are as the ſhining light, which ſhineth more and more to the perfect day: the way of the wicked is as darkneſs, and they know not at what they ſtumble at, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4. the light of the righteous rejoyced, but the lamp of the wicked ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l be put out: Mark, he goes from it who hates light, and tranſgreſſeth and abideth not in it, and ſo hath not God, <hi>Prov.</hi> 13. the poor and the deceitful man meets together, and the Lord lightens both their eyes: Now mark, here is the poor and the deceitful man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth enl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghtened, but he that doth ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, leaves the light, and doth not come to it, becauſe his deeds are evil, and that is his condemnation: And you that ſay the wicked man is not enl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghtned, the deceitful man is not enlightned, you deny the Scripture; read <hi>Prov.</hi> 29. and I ſay, that wiſdom did excel folly, as light darkneſs, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2. Mark, and know this light, and know this wiſdom, that excels folly and darkneſs, and com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rehends it, which gives to ſee the ſalvation Chriſt Jeſus, the light of the world, that doth enlighten every man that cometh in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the world, the Covenant of God to the Jews and Gentiles, and ſalvation to the ends of the earth; ſo he that believes in the ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſhall not abide in darkneſs, but ſhall have the light of life, and he that believeth in the light, ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a child of light, and Chriſt the Saviour of the world doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, and this light from him will let every man ſee his ſalvation, which believ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng in the light, receives power to become the Son of God, but hating the light, it is his condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and he doth enlighten all men that c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>meth into the world, that all might believe this is his end, but he that doth not believe, is condemned, and this is his condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the light, that light is come into the world: mark, into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he world, he doth not ſay altogether in his Saints, and men love darkneſs rather then the light: mark, men that darkneſs are in the world, and hates the light, and doth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116512:11"/> evil, and will not come to the light, left his deeds ſhould be reproved, but he that doth truth cometh to the light that his deeds may be manifeſt that they are wrought in God: Now he loveth darkneſs, becauſe his deeds are evil, and every one that doth evil, hateth the light, neither cometh to the light, leſt his deeds ſhould be reproved: mark, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe be of the world, and hath theſe the light, yea, how ſhould they know their evil deeds elſe? and will not come to the light, becauſe the light will reprove them, therefore men love darkneſs rather then the light; for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that doth evil, hateth the light, and this is his condemnation, the light that doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, ſaith John, he doth not ſay every Saint that cometh into the world, but every man; and light ſhineth in darkneſs, and darkneſs doth not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it. Now the Apoſtle writes to the Corinths, and told them, God had commanded light to ſhine out of darkneſs, which ſhined in their hearts, which did give them the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, theſe were them that were trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled on every ſide, and had the treaſure in earthen veſſels, and the excellency of the power of God in them, which was, which was not of the world, and theſe were not of the world that told the Corinths the end of the world was come, ſo this was a converted ſtate; ſo he hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned every one that cometh into the world, that all might believe, and he that doth not believe, is condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed already, but ſo many as receives him, he gives power to become the ſons of God, John was a burning and a ſhining light, and many did rejoyce in that for a ſeaſon, but Chriſt had a greater witneſs then John, and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived honour of men, but Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t received not honour of men, which enlightneth every m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n that cometh into the world; neither doth the light which they are enlightned withal rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive honour of men; and ſaith Jeſus Chriſt,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116512:11"/> who doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, the Prophets had propheſied that God would give him for a Covenant of light to the G ntiles, and a new covenant to the houſe of Iſrael, and ſalva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion to the ends of the earth; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d John was ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt to bear witneſs to the light, and ſaid, he was the true light that did enlighten every one that cometh into the wo ld, when Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the covenant of light to the Gentiles, and glory of Iſrael was come into the world, ſaith he, I am c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me a light into the world, he that follows me, ſhall not walk in darkneſs, but ſhall have the light of life, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. Now he that follows not the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght, abides in darkneſs, and they that were ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ching the Scriptures, and thought to have life there, and would not come to Chriſt the life, they had not the word of God abiding in them, neither heard they the voice of the Father at any time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor ſee his ſhape. Theſe were them that profeſſed the Scriptures, but in the tranſgreſſion of the life that gave them forth; and John writ to the converted, and told them the darkneſs was paſt, and the true light ſhined. Mark, heres a time they were in darkneſs, and a t me when light ſhined in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in the unconv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rted ſtate, and a time when light ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out of darkneſs in the converted eſtate: He that ſaith he is in the light, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>teth his brother, is in da kneſs until now: He that hates the light, is in darkneſs; out of the light, out of covenant; in the enmity he that loves his brother, abides in the light, and there is no occaſion of ſtumbling in him; but he that walks in darkneſs, is he that hates his brother, and knows not whither he goes, becauſe darkneſs hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> blinded his eyes, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. and this was the meſſage the Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s declared, that God was light, and in him was no darkneſs at all. Now whoſoever ſaith he hath fellowſhip with God, and walks in darkneſs, is a lyar, and doth not the truth, for the truth is in the l ght, out of darkneſs, 1 John 1. and the Apoſtle tells them that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116512:12"/> was of the Royal Prieſthood, that was the choſen gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, an holy Nation, a peculiar people, that they was called out of darkneſs into his marvellous light: mark, out of darkneſs, there was a time they was in it, that light ſhined in darkneſs, which while they was in darkneſs, they could not ſhew forth their fruits to the praiſe and glory of God, but being called out of darkneſs into the light, which comprehends darkneſs, 1 <hi>Pet,</hi> 2. and ſo ſuch as are ſtumbling at the light which enlightneth every ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that cometh into the world, are ſtumbling at every good and perfect gift, which cometh down from above from the Father of light, with whom there is no variableneſs nor ſhadow of changing, Jam. 1. the night is far ſpent, and the day at hand, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t us therefore put off the works of darkneſs, and put on the true light, which witneſs the night far ſpent, and the day at hand, that was to put off the works of darkneſs, and put on the Armor of light; the light is the Armor, that which manifeſts the works of darkneſs and the night, is the light, and that is the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. The J ws ſtood againſt the light when the Apoſtles preached Chriſt Jeſus, therefore ſaith he to them that had the Scriptures, ſhewing to them what the Prophets had ſaid; I have ſent thee a light to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and ſalvation to the ends of the earth, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. when the Gentiles heard this, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y were glad, Now the Profeſſors of this age which are wrangling againſt the light, they are wrangling againſt the ſalvation, for the ſame which is a light to the heathen, is ſalvation, yea to the ends of the earth; and Chriſt ſaith to the Phariſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, Take heed that the light that be in thee be not darkneſs: Now the Phariſees did not own Chriſt the light, ſo they was in the ſtate Iſaiah ſpeaks of, that put light for dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and darkneſs for light; and which John ſp aks of which light ſhined in darkneſs, which darkneſs could not comprehend; yet no man when he hath lighted a candle,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116512:12"/> putteth it in a ſecret place, neither under a buſhel, but on a candleſtick, that they may come to ſee the light; they was to ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the lamp, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. <hi>Numb.</hi> 8. <hi>Aaron</hi> was to light the Lamp, the ſeven lamps ſhall give light o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er againſt the Candleſtick, and Chriſt ſaith, let your lights be girded about, and your lights burning. Mark the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. The Philiſtims ſought to quench the light of Iſrael, ſo them that be in the ſame natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, now do: and war againſt it, 2 Sam. 21. the Lord had promiſed to his people a light, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8. which the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked hates, and wherefore is light given to him that is in miſery, ſaith Job? Now he that is in miſery, hath light given to him, you may ſee Job. 3. and why is light given to him whoſe way is hid, to bring him into the ways of God; it is the way, and therefore it is given to him, and therefore his way is hid: a land of darkneſs, and the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of death, without order, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re the light is as darkneſs in that land, as it is in this, which is ſtumbling at it, Job 10. they grope in the darkneſs without light, which are hating it, but God diſcovereth the deep things out of darkneſs, and bringeth to light the ſhadow of death, Job 12. and <hi>Bildad</hi> ſaid, the light of the wicked ſhall be put out, the light ſhall be dark in his Tabeanacle, and his can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll be put out with him, and he ſhall be driven from the light into darkneſs, and chaſed out of the world: of whom Job ſaid, How long will ye vex my ſoul? and told them they had reproched him; the light going from it, condemns out of the everlaſting world, and he goes into the world of wickedneſs, and upon whom doth not the light ariſe, ſaith <hi>Bildad,</hi> Job 25. and ſaith Job, the Lord bringeth the thing that is hid, forth to light: Now all come to know the thing that hath been hid come forth to light; you will all know what hath been in priſon, and by his light ſaith he, when I walked through darkneſs. Mark, by his light he walked through darkneſs, through
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116512:13"/> it. So here is light ſhining in darkneſs, and light ſhining out of darkneſs, and leading through it, to bring back his ſoul from the pit, to be enligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned with the light of the living, Job 29. and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s lightning is to the ends of the earth; from the wicked their light is with-helden, and the high arm ſhall be broken, The Lord (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) is my light and my ſalvation, and my God lightneth my eyes; now he that is the ſalvation, is the light, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. for with thee is the fountain of life, and in thy light we ſee light, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. He ſhall bring forth thy righteouſneſs as the light, and thy judgement as the Noon day. Mark, Righteouſneſs, Judgement, Light. Light is ſown for the righteous, and gladneſs for the upright in heart, but is condemna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion to the wicked, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97. unto the upright there ariſeth light in the darkneſs, and ſo it ſhines forth, and this is the light which gives the light of the knowledg of the Glory of God; heres a time out of darkneſs, joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the light, and they who are joyned to it, are one with it, ſo they that are joyned to the Lord, are one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and God hath ſhewed us light, ſaid <hi>David,</hi> who ſaid in the light he ſhould ſee more light; He ſaid, God had ſhewed him light, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. O houſe of Jacob, come let us walk in the light of the Lord. Mark, who come to walk in the light of the Lord, they come to walk in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God, Iſa. 2. for the Lord h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th ſent his word to Jacob, and hath enlightned Iſrael, and the people that walked in darkneſs, have ſeen a great light, and they that dwelt in the land of the ſhadow of death, hath light ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; this is in the Covenant with God, this do many hundreds witneſs, praiſes be the Lord. The light of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael ſhall be for a fire, and it ſhall burn and devour the B yars and Thorns in one day: Now Thorns and Bryars that which Thorns and Bryars comes out of, ſtands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the light, their feet are ſwift to run to do evil, and to ſhed innocent blood; and becauſe of theſe actions,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116512:13"/> they grope like blind men, they waited for light, but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity was found there in that path and way, Iſa. 59. and God will make dark the bright light of heaven, I will co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Sun with a cloud, and the Moon ſhall not give her light, Ezek. 32. and there ſhall be no night there, no need of a candle, nor of the Sun, for the Lord God giveth light, Chriſt Jeſus is the light which the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rd God hath given, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. Are not you ſuch that be Teachers, and be ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling at the light, and guide the blind that be in darkneſs; ſuch as need to be taught your ſelves, which cauſe the name of God to be blaſphemed among you, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. and Chriſt ſaith, as long as I am in the world, I am the light of the world, and this the condemnation, the light, ſaith Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt, he is the light of the world, <hi>Iohn</hi> 9. and light of the world, him by whom all things was formed, the lights was formed, the leſſer and the greater, the Sun ſhall be darkned, and the Moon ſhall ceaſe her ſhining, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the earth, and lo it was without form, and void, and the heavens they had no light, Iſa. 13. Jer. 4. and ſaith, after the tribulation the Sun ſhall be darkned, and the Moon ſhall not give her light, the ſtars of heaven ſhall fall, and the powers of heaven ſhall be ſhaken; for as the lightning that ſhineth from one part of heaven to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> part of heaven, ſo ſhall the coming of the Son of man be: So the Son of man comes in the clouds with great glory, but many ſhall ſay, Lo here is Chriſt, and lo there is Chriſt, but ſaith the true Chriſt, go not forth, who hath enlightned every man that cometh into the world; ſo every man having a light bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g turned to it, youl ſee him, and here is ſalvation to the ends of the earth; but who hate the light, it is their condemnat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on, the light of the Kings countenance is life, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16. have you light that be out of the Kings countenance, God is light, and he covers himſelf with light, majeſty, and honour, Pſalm 104. beware leſt you come to that end that ſtumble at the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:116512:14"/> light, that ſhall go to the Fathers, that ſhall never ſee light, and ſhall periſh like the Beaſt, ſuch hates light, which is their condemnation, Pſal. 49. the Arm of the Lord, and the light of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s countenance did ſave, but who are from the light of the countenance, and out of his Arm, they be out of the way of ſalvation, Pſalm 44. in thy light we ſhall ſee more light, ſaith <hi>David,</hi> O ſend out thy light, for it is truth, Pſalm 45. Chriſt is the light, Chriſt is truth, who is come, and take heed you that ſtumble at the light, leſt it be with-helden from you, as it is from the wicked, for they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with-helden from it, for it is their condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, from the wicked light is with-helden, for they hate it, Pſalm 38. Conſider me O Lord, and lighten mine eyes, leſt I ſle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p the ſleep of death, the light leadeth from the ſleep to the day from the night, for ſuch as be in the night, in the darkneſs, though in it the light ſhines, Chriſt comes upon them as a thief, the day is the Lords, and the night is the Lords, he prepareth the Moon and the Sun, and theſe were made by Chriſt the light, which doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten every man that cometh into the world, Pſalm 49. God ſpreadeth forth light, and all the lights that were made, were made by Chriſt, by what way is light parted, which ſcattereth the eaſt wind upon the earth, and when I ſit in darkneſs, the Lord will be a light to me. Mark, when he ſits in darkneſs, therefore heed the light, you may feel the light, then you may feel it bringing out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Mic.</hi> 7. and the brightneſs of God is as the light, which made perſecuting <hi>Saul</hi> fall to the earth, which did not believe in the light which did enlighten every man that cometh into the world, when the light ſhined about him, at laſt he came to find the light ſhin ng within him, and told others, that the light ſhined in their hearts, and them that were turned to the light, they come to be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers with the Saints in ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch as were tranſlated into the kingdom of the Son of God: and the Apoſtle
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116512:14"/> told the Saints they had a more ſure word of propheſie, to which they did well to take heed, until the day dawn, and the day ſtar ariſe in their hearts: Now you that are ſtumbling at the light, how far ſhort are you of this ſure word of Propheſie, as a light that ſhineth in a dark place, until the day dawning, and the day-ſtar ariſing in the heart, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. and are not you judging before the time, and the Lord will bring to light the hidden things of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and make manifeſt the counſel of the heart, you that are judging and ſtumbling at the light, are you not found in this condition, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. and the Sun and the Moon praiſeth the Lord, and the Stars of light which was made by Chriſt, and you that are ſtanding againſt ſalvation, Chriſt Jeſus that doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, that calls this ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, this ſalvation, a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral light, you have not yet ſeen your ſelves to be that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that lighteth a candle to ſweep the houſe, and hath found the piece of ſilver, <hi>Luke</hi> 15. ſo the Teachers that doth deny the light Chriſt, that doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, you are the Miniſters of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, that transforms themſelves into an Angel of light, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. and ſo you that do deny the light that doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten every man that cometh into the world, you l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteem the Rock of your ſalvation, which doth enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten every man that cometh into the world, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31. but you are them that lay the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>avie burdens upon the people, which makes them haavier, not lighter then your fathers, as you may read 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 10. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12. and ſee what burdens they laid upon the juſt, they that did tranſgreſs, but when you come to ſee the Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l come down from heaven, that lightens the earth with his glory, then ſhall you know the fall of Babylon, then may you come to ſee the light that lightneſs every one that cometh into the world, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. but all things that are reproved, are made manifeſt by the light; awake thou that ſleepeth,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116512:15"/> and ariſe from the dead, and Chriſt will give thee light; ſo they that ſleep, ſleep in the night; he th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t comes to the day, he comes to Chriſt, he is awakened and riſen from the dead, and witneſſeth Chriſt light he hath enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him withal: he is ariſen from the dead, and he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened, and he ſleeps not: he is out of ſleep, and among whom you ſhine as lights in the world, the children of the light, that are in the light that doth enlighten every one that cometh into the world, they are in Chriſt, theſe ſhines as lights in the world, theſe are converted, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the light in every one, Phil. 2. That which doth make manifeſt is light, and that which doth reprove is light, and all things that are reproved are made manifeſt by the light, for whatſoever doth make manifeſt, is light; for every one that doth evil, hateth the light, and will not come to the light, becauſe it will rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove him; this is the true light that doth enlighten every one that cometh into the world: What is the drunkard enl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghtned, and the ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the adulterer, and the Heathen: yea drunkenneſs is an evil deed, and theft is an evil deed, and adultery, and the murderer, and theſe doth evil, and theſe comes not to the light, leſt the light ſhould reprove them; and theſe with the light knows they ſhould not do ſo: and this is their condemation ſaith Chriſt the light, and their works are wrought out of God, and theſe are the children of diſobedience; now he that loveth the light, he cometh to the light, and bringeth his works to the light that they may be m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nifeſt that they are wrought in God, and he is not condemned, ſo times of darkneſs, the light not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d with the darkneſs, and the light ſhines in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and a time of putting light for darkneſs, and this the time when the word hath no place in them, and this is the time of the children of diſobedienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the Prince of the power of the Ayr rules i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them; this is the time of the unconverted under the power of Satan, in the darkneſs
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116512:15"/> not turned to the light; for this is the time that the god of the world blinding the eyes, that the light of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Goſpel ſhould not ſhine into them: for God having commanded light to ſhine out of darkneſs, to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God: Here the ſalvation is known, the everlaſting Covenant is known, and and all who denies the light, denies the ſalvation of God to the ends of the earth, and him the Prophet <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote, which God would raiſe up which the people ſhould hear; which doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, which is the Treaſury of Wiſdom and Knowledge, which light being turned to it, which comes from Chriſt, which ſhines in the heart, it gives the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: Now the firſt Prieſtho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and his lips was to preſerve th knowledge of the people; and they was to hear <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Jews was, which there was a ſeparation between them and the Gentiles; the ſecond Prieſthood Chriſt, is a light to the Gentiles; the Gentiles ſhall hear him, and the Jews ſhall hear him; and this is the Prophet Chriſt Jeſus that <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote of, which God would raiſe up, that people ſhould hear, and doth enlighten eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that cometh into the world, that all men might through him believe, ſo they were to hear <hi>Moſes,</hi> and he that doth not hear him is to be cut off, he goes from the light; they that walk in the light have unity one with another.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:116512:16"/>
            <p>TO all you Profeſſors, Prieſts, and Teachers who are in the darkneſs, and knows not the ſpirit in priſon, and knows not the light that ſhines in darkneſs, and darkneſs doth not comprehend it, but are the Infidels, whom the god of the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld hath blinded, to whom the Goſpel is hid, though they have the four Books, yet the Goſpel is hid, who are now ſtranging at the work of God, and do not believe that Chriſt hath enlightened every one that cometh into the world; ſo I ſhall give you ſome Scriptures to read, which will prove the Spirits and try them how contrary they be unto the Apoſtles ſpirit, Chriſt and the Saints; Chriſt went miniſtring to the ſpirit in priſon; he that readeth, let him underſtand whether this be a meaſure of the ſpirit yea or nay, or the ſpirit without meaſure which he miniſtred to, for he whom God hath ſent, ſpeaketh the word of God, <hi>John</hi> 3.34. for God gives not the ſpirit by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure unto him; Here Chriſt had not the Spirit by meaſure given unto him; and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. they would not boaſt themſelves above their meaſure: now here was meaſure, and not by meaſure, and Chriſt ſaith, who retained not the ſpirit by meaſure to his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, that he would ſend them the Comforter, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth, that he ſhould guide them into all Truth, for he ſhall not ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ak of himſelf, but whatſoever he ſhall hear that ſhall he ſpeak, and ſhew things to come, he ſhall glorifie me, for he ſhall receive of mine, ſaith Chriſt, and ſhew it unto you who believe the meaſure, receive of mine, whoſe is not by meaſure, and the Comforter when
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116512:16"/> he comes, he is to reprove the world of ſin, and of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, of judgement, and unbelief; of ſin, becauſe they do not believe. Now mind all the large Book of God, the ſpirit of Truth, which leads the Saints into all Truth, which receives of Chriſt, and ſhews it unto his Diſciples, who be in their meaſure, he ſhall reprove the world becauſe they do not believe, and of ſin, of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and of judgement. Now the Comforter whom Chriſt will ſend, take of his, and ſhew it to the Diſciples who reprove the world: Now mind this, and read this, whether this be a meaſure yea or nay, which c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mes from him who received not the Spirit by meaſure, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16. He that leads the believers into all Truth, reprove the unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers in the world of ſin, of judgmens, and righteouſneſs, ſo he that is led into all Truth ſees that which is reproved with the ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it of Truth that leads, and when Chriſt ſaith he ſhall take of mine and ſhew it unto you, whether this be a meaſure yea or nay, from him whom God gave the ſpirit not by meaſure too: And ſaith the Lord by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, It ſhall come to paſs in the laſt days, I will pour out my ſpirit upon all fleſh, and my ſons and my daughters ſhall propheſie, young men ſhall ſee viſions, old men ſhall dream dreams, and on my handmaids will I pour out my ſpirit in thoſe days, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d they ſhall propheſie; <hi>Acts</hi> 2.17, 18. Look you Deceivers, Here the Lord ſaith he will pour out of his ſpirit: mark the word, out of it upon all fleſh: What? young men, and old men, and ſons, and daughters, and maids? All theſe to have the ſpirit of the Lord upon all fleſh poured! Here ſay they, theſe deny the means: then here mark the word out of the Lords ſpirit, and the notable day of the Lord is coming, and whoſoever calleth on the name of the Lord ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.22, the God of the ſpirits of all fleſh is known: and ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who would not boaſt himſelf above his own meaſure, that which may be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116512:17"/> known of God is manifeſt in them, God hath ſhewed it unto them, with this which was of God manifeſt in them, they knew covetouſneſs, malice, murder, deceit, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs, who knows the judgement of God was upon ſuch things; <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. and that they were worthy of death that not only do the ſame, but have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leaſure in them that do them, therefore is the wrath of God revealed from heaven againſt all the ungodlineſs and unrighteous of men; ſo whether this of God manifeſt in them, which God ſhewed unto them, with which they knew unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Gods judgement upon them that do it, and they are worthy of death, whether this be a meaſure yea of nay which is of God which he hath ſhewed to them, and what was that in them that did by nature the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Law, which ſhewed the works of the Law written in their hearts: M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rk, written: But ſhall not this judge them that have the outward Law, but are out of the life of it, and ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. the manifeſtation of the ſpirit is given to every man to profit withal: Now mark here the ſpirits manifeſtation is given to every one to profit withal; there are diverſities of gifts but by the ſame ſpirit, and ſo the manifeſtation of it is given to every man to profit withal: Mark, to one is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the ſpirit of Wiſdom, to another the ſpirit of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, to another the gifts of healing, to another the ſpirit of diſcerning, to another tongues, but all theſe worketh the one and the ſelf ſame ſpirit, dividing to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſeverally as he will; now to every man ſeverally as he will: And ſaith the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Tit,</hi> 2.11, 12. the grace of God that brings ſalvation, hath appeared to all men, teaching us to deny ungodlineſs and worldly luſt, and to live ſoberly and righteouſly: Now you that turn this grace that brings ſalvation into wantonneſs, may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, and ſay it hath not appeared to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll men, which teacheth the Saints which by grace are ſaved; and ſaith
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116512:17"/> 
               <hi>Jude,</hi> behold the Lord cometh with ten thouſand of his Saints to ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cute Judgment upon all, to convince all that are ungodly amongſt them, of their ungodl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deeds they have ungodly commited, &amp; of all their ſpeeches which ungodly ſinners have ſpoken againſt him. Here mark a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, that cometh with ten thouſands of his Saints, to convince all of ungodly deeds, and their hard ſpeeches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> now is here all of their hard ſpeeches &amp; all of their ungodly deeds, none left out but all? Looke you blind what is that which convinceth all of their ungodly deeds and hard ſpeeches, is not that the ſpirit of the Lord which is now come and coming to raigne, and to reprove the world, who will raigne, and be king and Judg, and have not you all ſomthing in you that doth reprove you for your hard ſpeeches and your ungodly deeds, the ungod lyeſt of you all, and who live in your hard ſpeeches, and the Apoſtle wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Gentiles, he ſaith: But unto every one of us is given grace according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt, now marke: here is the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt, who lighteth every man that cometh into the world, that all men through him might believe; he that believeth is ſaved and he that doth not, is condemned, and this is the condemnation that light is come into the world, and men love darkneſs rather then light, becauſe their deeds be evil: now every man being enlightened that cometh into the world, one he loves the light, and brings his deeds to the light that with the light he may ſee whether they be wrought in God, &amp; the other he hates the light, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that his deeds be evill, and he will not bring his deeds to the light becauſe he knowes that the light will reprove him, that hates light whoſe deeds are evill, whom Chriſt enlightened knowes that the light will reprove him: therefore the will not come to the light becauſe his deeds are evill; and I will give him for a light to the Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iles, ſalvation to the ends of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> earth and what is that which
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116512:18"/> the children that wlaketh according to the courſe of this world, the Prince of the power of the Ayre that works in the children of diſobedience: what is that which they are diſobedient to? a conſider, mark, and read your ſelves which being d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſobedient, they walked according to the courſe of the world and the Prince of the power of the ayre which now worketh in the children of diſobedience; now mark what diſobedience is too: and him that hath an eare let him read and hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: and ſaith the Apoſtle to the Coloſſians, the wrath of God cometh upon the ch ldren of diſobedience Come you profeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs let us ſee? is not this ſomthing of God that is diſobeyed is it not that is of God manifeſt in them, which God hath ſhewed, which lets them ſee Gods Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gment is upon ſuch things, when they act unrighteouſly? is not this the meaſure of God? mark: and the Spirit that is in priſon and the Spirit of God, that is grieved; and ye profeſſors come let us read the Talents, and reckon with you, and ſee who it is that hath hid the Lords money in the earth, come you that have gained, enter you into your Maſters ioy; go thou that hath hid the Lords money in the earth, into utter darkneſs; take it from him; and give it to him that hath, and every man ſhall have his reward according to his workes, and ſo the Lord hath given to every man ſeverally according to his abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity here, mark: every man ſeverally according to his ability read if you it can hear and now is the Lord coming to, call every man ſeverally to acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unt to which he hath given ſeverally, according to his ability, and now the wicked and ſlothful ſervant which hid the Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s money in the earth will be found out, and the Lords money will be taken from him, although he hath hidden it to, him the Lords commands hath been grevous; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to us th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y are not who love G d; becauſe we keep his c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mmandements, and God who gave his Son for a covenant of light to lighten every man that cometh into the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld and ſaith the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116512:18"/> Apoſtle I ſay through the grace given unto me to every man that is amongſt you, not to thinke of himſelfe more highly then he ought to think, but ſoberly, according as God hath dealt to every man a meaſure of faith read and marke h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re is a meaſure of faith, and ſaith the Apoſtle, as every man hath received the gift, even ſo let him mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, as a good ſteward of the manifold graces of God, for the grace of God hath appeared to all men, now you good ſtewards, now you bad ſtewards which turn the grace of God into laſciviouſnes you will be reckoned withall, you ſhall have your reward: but ſaith the world, muſt every man miniſter as he hath received the gift, yea but let him ſpeak as the Oracle of God, and let him doe it of the ability which God hath given him, and ſaith <hi>John</hi> in the Revelation, every man ſhall be Judged, according to his workes, read and underſtand I; ſay unto you for every idle word that men ſhall ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ak, they ſhall give an account therof in the day of Judgment, ſo you that name the name of Chriſt, depart from iniq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity, the ſon of man ſhall come in the glory of his father with his Angels, then ſhall he reward every man according to his workes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.21. him who is g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne into a far country, and hath given the Talents, and to every of you ſeverally according to your abilities, and will render to every man according to his deeds, for every man having a light from Chriſt who lighteth every man that cometh into the world with the light, he ſhall ſee his evill deeds, which comes from Chriſt, who will render to every man according to his deeds, the revelation of the righteous Judgment of God <hi>Ro.</hi> 2.6. and further I ſay unto you, if any man have not the ſpirit of Chriſt, he is none of his, and lif Chriſt be in you, the body is dead, but the ſpirit is life, becauſe of righteouſneſs, ſo let the light that from Chriſt cometh, now examine, for the Lord is appearing; you that have according to your abilities, ſmite not your fellow ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vants, and think you
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116512:19"/> not that the Lord delayeth the time of his coming be, not as them which ſaith let us eat and drinke, for to morow we ſhall dye, and as the Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtle ſaith to the <hi>Epheſians.</hi> 3.9. and to make all men ſee what is the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſh p of the miſtery which from the begin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of the world hath been hid in God, who created all things by Jeſus Chriſt. read and underſtand every one with the light that cometh from Chriſt the miſtery, which will be your condemnation, elſe if you believe not in it, and this is to all that ſtumble at the worke of the ſpirit of God, the manifeſtation of it which is given to every man to Profit with all: and come you profeſſors, let vs read the parable who ſtumble at it, a ſower went forth to ſow, and ſome ſeed fell on the high way ground, and ſome on ſtony ground, and ſome on thorny ground; and the ſeed is the word, and the ſon of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n is the ſeeds-man: he that hath an ear let him hear: and Look now all you profeſſors which ground you are, and what you have brought forth, and whether the wicked ſeeds-man have not gotten his ſeed into your g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ound: he that hath an eare let him heare it: come read another parable of the labourers going into the vineyard, and agreeing with every man for a peny. <hi>Mat.</hi> 20 every man is to have his peny, the laſt that went in as well as the firſt, ſo the laſt ſhall be firſt, and the firſt laſt, for many are called but few choſen: he that hath an eare let him heare: There is a Promiſe ſpoken to <hi>Cain,</hi> it he did well he ſhould be accepted, and <hi>Eſau</hi> had a birthright and deſpiſed it, now here you may ſay: we hold for free will, nay it is not in him that willeth, but by grace that you are ſaved, and ſtand ſtill and ſee your ſalvation, and you that be children of light, put on the armor of light, that you may come into the unity of the faith of the knowledg of the ſon of God, unto a perfect man unto the meaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the ſtature of the fullneſs of Chriſt that hence forth you be no more children toſſed to and fro <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116512:19"/> ſaith the Lord, I will make a new Covenant, the covenant which the Lord will write in their hearts, and put his ſpirit into their inward parts; by which they ſhould all come to know the Lord, him by whom the world was made, now every one of you mind this Law written in your hearts, and this ſpirit put in your inward pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts, that you need not ſay know the Lord, that you may witneſs the promiſe of God before the world begun, but ſaith the world and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, if every one muſt come to witneſs the Law of God written in their hearts, and the ſpirit put in their inward parts, what muſt we do with our Teachers, we come to witneſs that we need not any man to teach us to know the Lord, having the Law written in our hearts, and the ſpirit put in our inward parts. This is the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of life, the everlaſting covenant, which decayeth not, nor changeth not, and here is the way to the Father, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which no man comes to the Father, and here is the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Prieſthood, the end of the firſt prieſthood, whoſe lips were to preſerve knowledge, but now ſaith Chriſt, learn of me the ſecond prieſthood, and ſaith the Apoſtle, that you grow up in the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt, in whom are hid the treaſure of wiſdom and knowledge, ſo you are brought of the firſt p ieſthood, that doth change to Chriſt the ſecond Prieſthood that doth not change, and of the firſt covenant that doth decay, to the everlaſting co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant that doth not decay, Chriſt Jeſus, the covenant of light, from whence every one of you have a light, that you might believe in the covenant of light, if you do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the covenant of light, you are condemned, for light is come into the world, and men loves darkneſs rather then light, becauſe their deeds be evil, and I am come a light into the world (ſaith Chriſt) that whoſoever believeth in me ſhould not abide in darkneſs, but ſhould have the light of life, and believe in the light, that you may be children of light, and you that do not believe in the light, whoſe deeds
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116512:20"/> are evil, but hate it, you are that one who with the light is condemned, therefore now you have time, prize it, ſeek the Lord whilſt he may be found, and call upon him whilſt he is nigh, leſt you ſay time is paſt, for the rich gluttons time was, therefore whilſt time is not paſt, conſider, and ſearch your ſelves, and ſee if you be not them that hate the light, and ſo are the builders that ſtumble at the corner ſtone, for them that hated the light, and did not believe in the light, did ſo in ages paſt; I am the light of the world, and doth enlighten every one that come<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h into the world, ſaith Chriſt, who ſaith learn of me, this is my beloved Son, hear you him, ſaith G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, here is your Teacher, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you that hate the light, do not learn of Chriſt, and will not have him to be your king to reign over you, him to whom all power in heaven and earth is given, who bears his government upon his ſhoulders, who now is come to rei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, who lighteth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man that cometh into the world, whe will give to every man a reward according to his deeds, whether they be good or evil, ſo every man with the light that comes from Chriſt will ſee his deeds, him th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t hates it, and him that loves it, and him that will not bring his deeds to the light, becauſe the light will reprove him that is his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, and he ſhall have a reward according to his deeds, and the Lord is come to reckon with you, and to look for fruit, and now is the Ax laid to your root, and every tree of you that beareth not good fruit, muſt be hevven dovvn, and caſt into the fire, from them vvho are the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> vvhich the promiſe is to, vvhen he vvas in the u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>circumciſion, ſuch as knovv the God of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:116512:20"/>
            <head>An eſtabliſhing Note to all friends upon the Earth.</head>
            <p>WIth the wiſe upon earth in their own wiſdom, and the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eateſt knowers up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth in their own k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owledge, and the greateſt underſtanding men in their underſtanding, and the greateſt learned Doct r in their languages upon earth was Chriſt, amo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g them who was born not by the will of man, was the Son of God among them, theſe before mentioned, was he judged a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lled the ſon of <hi>Ioſeph;</hi> and they ſaid his B eth en and his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they knew, ſo looked upon the Son of God to be natural, and ſo ſaying his father and moth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r and B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n were with him whom they knew: Is not this the Son of <hi>Ioſeph?</hi> and qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtioned from whence had this man this wiſd m? So with all theſe was him by whom the world was made looked upon as natural, a natural birth by the will of man: Him that was glorified with the Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world began, who enlightneth every man that cometh into the world, him by which it was made and all things created, that all men through him might believe: Therefore he enlightneth every man, and ſaith, Believe in the light, that you may become children of the light, which the wiſe of the earth ſaid they believed in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture declared forth from the light, but not in the light it ſelf. And now in this age, the wiſe in the earth in their
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:116512:21"/> own wiſdom, and the great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt underſtandings in their Politician, and the greateſt knowers that be in their own knowledge of the Scriptures, and the large Doctors in their lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ning, the greateſt Students and Diſputers, and the great Writers, judgeth and calleth the light that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightneth every man that c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>meth into the world, an natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral light; this is ſo called by them, and among them. The light the Son of God which doth enlighteneth every man that cometh into the world, which all theſe S udents before-men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ioned call a natural light; nay ſome of them calls it a natural conſcience, the light which the Son of God doth e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lightan every one that cometh into the world withal, him by whom it was made, that all men through him might believe; and he ſaith, Believe in the light, that you may become children of the light. But theſe witty wiſe ones in their wiſdom, knowledge, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding ſay, they believe the Scriptures, Prophets words, Chriſts words, Apoſtles words; But the light which doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, by whom it was made, which was glorified with the Father before the world began, is the checks of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural conſcience, and this light is a natural light, ſay they, and is the light ſay we which is given to all men to beli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve in the light, which who do not believe in the light, is condemned already, is with the light condemned, that they who believe in the l ght ſhall never be condemned, nor never come into condemnation, nor never be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; for he believeth in that which makes manifeſt that which is to be confounded. Now the Phariſees which ſearch the Scriptures, Doctors, Rabbies, great learned men which ſearch the Scriptures, in them think to have eternal life, they did believe the Scriptures, they had <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and the Prophets, But they did not believe in the light, being out of <hi>Moſes</hi> light, and the Prophets light, ſo ſaw not Chriſt the light, with which <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:116512:21"/> ſaw him when he came, they having the words, but out of the light; theſe were them which were blind guides to the people, which lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> people, and believed not in the light which enlightned every man that c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>meth into the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rld; but looked at him as a carnal man, a natural man, and knew him not the Son of God, who lighteth every man that cometh into the wo ld, the Son of God by whom it was made; and theſe wiſe upon earth now in their own wiſdom, and the great und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſt nding and knowers in their own knowledge which they now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, Chriſts and the Apoſtles words, declared from the light, and they themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the light, and out of it, and not believing in it, the light which doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, him by whom it was made, theſe knew not the Scriptures, that believe not in the light, though they have them read among them every firſt day, as the Jews had them read among th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m every Sabbath day, yet knew not the voice of the Prophets, nor of God, nor of his Son, ſo now all theſe in this age that have the Scriptures read among them every firſt day, and believeth not in the light, which doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, ſeeth not Chriſt Jeſus the ſame to day, yeſterday, and for ever, him by whom the world was made, who was glorified with the Father before the world began, which the children of the light which believe in the light that enlightneth every man that cometh into the world, whoſe food is the bread of life that cometh from above, whoſe water is the water of life, which knows the living ſprings, theſe comes to know the Scriptures, the Prophets words declared from the light, the fulfilling of them; C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riſts words declared from the light, and the fulfilling of them, and the Apoſtles words declared forth from the life, and the fulfilling of them; and theſe that be in the light, believe in the light, have unity in the light, from which
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:116512:22"/> declared forth the Word was, and unity with the words which declared forth from the light was, and to them are reconciled; but they that believe not in the light which enlightneth every man that cometh into the world, they be all on heaps and ſtrife about the Prophets words, Chriſts words, and the Apoſtles words, which was dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ared forth from the light, they that b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lieve not in the light, the greateſt ſtudents upon the earth, diſputers, underſtandings, and knowers in their own knowledge, knoweth not he Scrip ures, nor are not reconciled to them, which believe not in the light wh ch lighteth every man that cometh into the world; theſe are the blind guides in theſe our days, was and is in all ages, ſuch as believeth not in the light which enlighteneth every man that cometh into the world, and they are in the diſputings, and ſtrife, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, being in the contention about the words declared from the light, the Scriptures, the words of Chriſt, the Prophets, and the Apoſtles, ſo being in the dark, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in the light which enl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghtneth every one that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth inro the world; theres the ſtumbling, and theres the perſecuter which was ever blind, which ſtumbles at the light which enlightneth every man that cometh into the world, which is the way, &amp; every man that have light from the way, and the light is the truth which enlightneth every man that cometh into the world, that all men through him might believe: And here is the truth in the inward parts; ſo all you ſtumbling at the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght, you ſtumble at the way, and you ſtumble at the truth, and you ſtumble at the life; in him was light, that lighteth every one that cometh into the world, and the light is the life of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n: now is it not appearing, and doth it not appear among all the wiſe of the earth in their own wiſdom, ſuch as profeſs the Scriptures declared from the light, and believeth not in the light which enlightneth every man that cometh into the world; how they confound one another: Yea the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116512:22"/> Doctors and great learned Rabbies, the great knowing men, the great un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ders, ſuch as believe not in the light, how they confound one another, and one anothers meanings they do get, that are blind to the Scriptures, Is it not apparent among you all beholders? Now ſuch as believe in the light, ſhall not be condemned. Mark, and theſe become children of the light, and Chriſt gives them an underſtanding, who is the wiſdom of God, and they grow up in the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus, who hath the Treaſury of Wiſdom and Knowledge, theſe com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rehend the world, and their knowledge, wiſdom, and un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which believe not in the light, with which light is all condenſed and confounded, in which light the children of light believing, which was glorified with the Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the world began, which is not natural, but ſpiritual, not created, but that by which all things was created, and theſe that are here raigns over the world, and witneſſeth him by whom it was made, and treads all the other which believes not in the light, which is out of the light, under foot, as unſavoury, under foot of man, theſe are the light of the world, theſe are the ſalt of the earth.</p>
            <p>Them that hold up Synagogues, Temple, changeable Prieſthood, that took Tythes, did not believe in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Prieſt, the light which enlightneth every man that cometh into the world, the unchangeable Prieſt, after the order of Melchiſedech; this was in the days of the Phariſees, chief Prieſts, in the days of Chriſt in the fleſh then, and theſe withſtood the light that did enlighten every men that cometh into the world, that all men through him might believe. Now in our dayes and age, ſuch as holds up the prieſts which take Tythes, and hath Temple, and Synagogue, and the chief place in the Aſſembly, as the phariſees had, which was in the tranſgreſſion out of the life of the Scriptures, which Chriſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:116512:23"/> cryed woe againſt theſe now in this age doth not believe in the light, which doth enlighten every man that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eth into the world as the Phariſees and chief Prieſts did not: theſe I ſay that takes tithes, and holds up the Prieſts with tithes that hath the Synagogue &amp; Temple &amp; the chiefeſt place in the aſſembly, which wo Chriſt cryed againſt theſe, believe not in him, in that Chriſt which enlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth every man that cometh into the world, that all men through him might believe, who are to believe in the light according to Chriſt command, and are to learn of him according to Gods command, of Chriſt the light which doth enlighten every one that cometh into the world, every man is to hear him, every man is to learn of him, hear him ſaith God, this is my beloved Son hear ye him, every man who heareth the light which Chriſt Jeſus hath enlightened him withall, he heareth Chriſt, who ſaith, learn of me, I am the way, the truth and the life, and no man cometh to the way but by me, who was glorified with the Father before the world began, now all the ſtudents in the world which ſtand againſt the light, ſuch as hold up Synagogue, Temple and carnal worſhip, and obſerves dayes and times, calls the light which doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, an natural light, or the checks of an natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, or a created light; the light that doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, by whom it was made, and all things created, nothing that was created; but was created by him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Mark, by him: and was before it was created, which doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, that all men through him might believe; ſo theſe which are holding up Temple, Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, Tithes, and Prieſt that takes them which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the Scriptures, declared forth from the light, not believing in it, but making a trade of the words, diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:116512:23"/> contending and are in ſtrife about them the light, in the dark, about the words that came from the light, the holy Scriptures that were given forth, to be read. Mark, to be believed in, to be practiſed, for <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets they was in the light, &amp; they ſpake forth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from the light, and they ſpake them forth to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled; and what they wrote they wrote to be fulfilled, and Chriſt Jeſus the light came to fulfil what was wrote of him, and they ſaw; Moſes and the Prophets ſaw what muſt come to fulfil their words; Chriſt Jeſus which did come to fulfil their words, and the Jews that were out of the light, ſaw not Chriſt when he was come to fulfil <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and the Prophets words, the Jews profeſſed, and the Apoſtles who witneſſed Chriſt, and the Diſciples, who was come to fulfil what was written of him; they ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Jews, Phariſees, and to the great wiſe Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, great knowing men who profeſſed <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets that a <hi>Meſ ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was to come, they being out of the light, they ſhewed unto them that Jeſus was the Chriſt out of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> and the Prophets, which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed but did not believe in the light; ſo they ſhewed the fulfilling of the Prophets, and the fulfilling of <hi>Moſes</hi> words and preached to them him that was come, which did fulfil them, which they that did believe in the light come to ſee the ſecond Prieſt-hood, who turned were from the firſt Prieſt-hood, Temple, Synagogue, Prieſt-hood that took Tiths. But them that did not believe in the light, ſtumbled at the Apoſtles words, and ſtumbled at the light, which doth enlighten every one that cometh into the world; theſe Builders rejected the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orner-ſtone, and counted themſelves unworthy of e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ernal life, and though they profeſſed <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets words, but believed not in the light, as all our Profeſſors and Prieſts of the world in our dayes, which believeth not in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:116512:24"/> the light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world, judging themſelves unworthy of eternal life, yet profeſſing <hi>Moſes,</hi> Chriſt, and the Apoſtles words; but ſeeth not the fulfilling of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, nor Chriſts words and Apoſtles words, ſuch as be out of the light, that believes not in it, theſe are now haling out of the Synagogue, priſoning, and beating, and perſecuting that believe not in the light, that enlighteneth every man that cometh into the world, as the Jews did out of their Temple, which priſoned and perſecuted as thoſe do, and haled before Magiſtrates, which fulfil choiſe words, they that did ſo believed not in the light, but were out of the light, and ſo they know not the Son nor the Father: take notice of this, all prieſts and people, who are haling now out of the Synagogues, who are the generation that are fulfilling Chriſts words, that the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous blood may come upon you all. But the Lamb hath gotten the victory, and the Saints ſings over you all, them that be out of the light be out of truth, which an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers light and truth in every man, which is the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of all that are out of the light, and hate it, and this is the word of the Lord God to you, and all that ſees the light ſees their ſalvation, they that believe in the light and in that do dwell which condemn all the world, and none cometh to everlaſting life, but who cometh to the light, which doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, who is the life and as every man cometh to the light which he is enlightened withal, he cometh to the life of man, and he cometh to the way to the Father, which no man cometh to the way to the Father, but who cometh to the light, which enlighteneth him and every one that cometh into the world, by which light all things were made, and none cometh to truth but who cometh to the light, which doth enlighten every one that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:116512:24"/> into the world, him by whom the world was made, glorified with the Father before the world began, and no man cometh to the glorious Goſpel, which is the Image of God, but who cometh to the light which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteneth every man that cometh into the world and no man receiveth the power to become the Sons of God, but who receiveth the light which cometh from Chriſt, which is the power of God, who doth enlighten every one that cometh into the world, him by whom it was made, nor no man cometh to the truth in the inward parts, but ſuch as cometh to the light, which doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten every one that cometh into the world, him by whom it was made, who doth enligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en every man that cometh into the world; who is the truth in the inward parts, there is it to be heard, found, ſeen, and received, with that is Chriſt the miſtery the light ſeen, with the light which comes from him, which is the truth in the inward parts; with this is the Kingdom of God ſeen, which hath no end, and here is the light of the Goſpel known, which is the Image of God, with this is the God of this World ſeen with the light which comes from him, which was glorified with the Father before the world began. Take notice of this all ye children of light, and all they that do withſtand the light, which doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, him by whom it was made, glorified with the Father before the world began, they do withſtand the way; for every one coming into the world, having a light that comes from the way, lets him ſee the way, and a light from the life lets him ſee the life, and a light from the truth lets him ſee the truth, and a light from the word lets him ſee the words, and lets him ſee the word that was in the beginning before the world was: this light from the way to the Father, with which they know the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:116512:25"/> way to the Father into the Kingdom of God, where there is no ſhadow, a light from him which was glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with the Father before the World began, which light ſhining in the heart, gives them the light of the glory of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, and this is the treaſure in earthen veſſels; now every man having a light from the truth which is the Chriſt, which is the way to the Father the God of all truth, here you need not go forth to ask where you ſhall find truth, for it is in your inward parts, and as that teacheth you, and you abide in it, you continue in the Son, and in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from whence it comes, and every man having a light from Chriſt, who is the light, with which light hee will ſee him that comes from him, which light leads to him that he may believe in him, he ſhall not come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to condemnation; he need not to ſay, lo here is Chriſt, lo there's Chriſt, he that believeth in the light that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteneth every man that cometh into the world: now every man believing in the light, which enlighteneth every man that cometh into the world, with which they be lighted withal, here's the true belief, then they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in Chriſt, who is the light. Mark, in him, for the Phariſees believed, had the letter, who did not believe in the light, ſo was blind; ſo are all now who do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in the light, which lighteth every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the world, therefore they that do not believe in the light, which doth enlighten every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the World, that they might believe through him: But talkes of a belief, becauſe the Scriptures de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, and believes not in the light, they believe not in the truth, the devils, which be out of the light, which is the truth, can talk of the Scriptures as well as all the World, which is out of the light, out of truth, which doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:116512:25"/> that all men through him might believe, they that withſtand the light that enlighteneth every man that cometh into the world withſtands the way, and they that ſtumble at it, ſtumble at the way, and they that ſtumble at the light that lighteth every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the world, they ſtumble at truth, and they know not Chriſt, which doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world; and Prieſt and people knows not <hi>John</hi> the meſſenger of Chriſt, ſent from God to bear witneſs to this true light, that doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten every man that cometh into the world, who ſuffered death by the powers of the earth for bearing his righteous teſtimony againſt the unrighteous, and the powers of the earth, and the great Rabbies ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth againſt them now, and doth caſt them into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that are the witneſſes of this light, this true light, that doth enlighten every one that cometh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, that all men through him might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, who is the Son of God, and againſt this light which doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, the powers of the earth, and the rulers of the earth, and the chief Prieſts gathered Councels together againſt, who lighted every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the world, him by whom it was made, and ſo all they that are ſtumbling at the light, which doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, which is the Covenant of God, the Covenant of light, they are ſtumbling at the Covenant, and all them; And thoſe that keep people from the light, that doth enlighten every man that cometh into the world, keep people from the Covenant of God, the Covenant of light, the Covenant of life, the Covenant of peace; and to you this is the word of the Lord God, and every man coming into the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:116512:26"/> world, being enlightened with the Covenant of light, he loving the light, and receiving the light, he receives the Covenant; but hating the light he goes into the evil deeds, and this is the light doth make them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, and this his condemnation that hates it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the light and not believing in it, and this the lig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> torments the evil doer, and reprooves him and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> manifeſt his wayes and deeds, and this is the light that makes manifeſt him that abode not in truth, that ſpeaks a lie, that's from the truth, from the light, with the light condemned, which anſwers the light in every mans conſcience; ſo this is the word of the Lord God.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Given forth in Lanſon Caſtle.</hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>G. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
